NOTICE OF RESIGNATION
‪（辞职䟽）
Please stay healthy, Your Royal Highness.
‪请您保重 邸下
I hope you won't be lonely.
‪请不要感到孤单
NOTICE OF RESIGNATION
‪（辞职䟽）
Lord Jung!
‪公子
Is it true that you're leaving the Capital?
‪你要离开都城的事是真的吗？
Yes, I'm afraid it just happened that way.
‪是的 事情莫名就变成这样了
How can you be this indifferent?
‪你真是无情
Despite my confessions of longing for you,
‪我都说了还想再见到你 ‪很期待见到你
you're leaving.
‪你怎么能就此离去？
Lady So-eun…
‪你…
Please don't leave.
‪你不要走
My feelings for you only just started to grow.
‪我才刚喜欢上你
I've only just been made aware of them.
‪我才刚明白自己的心意
So how can you leave like this?
‪你怎么能如此无情地离去呢？
I apologize…
‪很抱歉
for not realizing…
‪我没察觉…
your feelings for me.
‪你对我的一片心意
It was a pleasure
‪这是一段美好的缘分
to have…
‪能认识你…
met you.
‪我何其有幸
Are you sure?
‪那是真的吗？
Yes, the farewell would have brought anyone to tears.
‪是啊 那个场面简直令人无法不掉泪
Audacious, is it not?
‪但也真是唐突对吧？
A lady hoping to be the Crown Princess
‪一个要成为世子嫔的女人
has given her heart to another.
‪心里居然有别的男人
I hope you're not going to let this grave piece of information
‪这种事应该不会 ‪只用来当作酒席上的下酒菜
stay between just us.
‪说说就带过去吧？
What? I don't think I follow.
‪这是什么意思？
His Majesty is looking to join forces with the Minister of Personnel
‪殿下为了牵制尚宪君大监
to regulate Lord Sangheon's authority.
‪打算要和吏判联手
Rumor has it that the Crown Prince already met with Minister Shin's daughter.
‪据说世子也已经见过吏判之女了
Wait.
‪等等
Are you saying that she has already been chosen as
‪那表示她已经被选定为世子嫔了
the future Crown Princess?
‪是这个意思吗？
That all depends on you now.
‪这现在就取决于叔父了
The Minister of War's daughter is whom Lord Sangheon wants as the Crown Princess.
‪对于想让兵判之女 ‪当上世子嫔的尚宪君大监
This information would surely grab his attention.
‪应该会对此事甚感兴趣
Do you not agree?
‪你说是不是？
Gosh.
‪天啊
Are you saying
‪所以说
that the Minister of Personnel's daughter harbors feelings for another man?
‪吏判之女另有心上人了？
Yes, and if you give me the word,
‪没错 只要你开口
I would gladly notify the Queen Dowager this second.
‪我可以现在立刻就去大妃殿告发此事
I could even find a witness to present.
‪若需要证人我也可以找来
What is it that you want in return?
‪您想从我这得到什么回报？
Pardon?
‪什么？
What I want in return?
‪我想得到什么回报？
If this matter is swayed in my direction,
‪只要顺利解决这件事
I will make sure to repay you in the capacity you desire.
‪我将重重报答您对我的恩情
This is the future Queen we're discussing.
‪这是将来要成为朝鲜国母的人
A lady
‪她竟爱慕其他男人
who harbors feelings for another man? The Crown Prince's tutor, no less?
‪况且对象还是世子的老师
I advise that it would be wise of you to remove her name from the process
‪因此在事情变得一发不可收拾前
before this matter causes serious problems.
‪你最好下令将那孩子的名字 ‪从拣择名单中剔除
It cannot end at just that.
‪光是那样还不够
As Your Highness implied,
‪就如大妃娘娘所言
the Minister of Personnel made a mockery out of the royal family.
‪她可是侮辱王室的可憎之人
What is considered as our nation's sacred event was discredited
‪她误了国运关天的事情
so eliminating her from the process cannot be enough.
‪当然不能仅将她 ‪从拣择名单上除名就算了
Her being eliminated from the process
‪倘若吏判的女儿落聘
will let you choose whomever you desire as Crown Princess,
‪就能依你的意思选定世子嫔
so what more could you want?
‪你还想要什么？
The Minister of Personnel put forth his daughter as a candidate
‪隐瞒子女的秘密 上呈闺女单
despite her transgression and therefore, he should also answer for his crime.
‪吏曹判书也应当被问罪才对
It was I who ignored my daughter's pleading
‪小女请臣不要上缴名单
and entered her as a candidate
‪是我罔顾她的意见
for the Crown Princess selection.
‪擅自主张进行了此事
Please reprove this foolish father
‪要怪就请责怪我这没出息的父亲
for not realizing where his daughter's heart lies.
‪未能察觉女儿的心思
How could this be your fault?
‪那怎么会是你的错呢？
I let my greed get the best of me which resulted in the loss of a loyal subject.
‪我的贪念让我失去得力大臣
I am the one…
‪该被埋怨的人
who should be blamed.
‪是我才对
I will never be able
‪这份罪过
to seek forgiveness from Your Majesty,
‪是无法被殿下和邸下
His Royal Highness, and the other officials.
‪还有朝廷大臣们饶恕的
It was I who ignored my daughter's pleading
‪小女请臣不要上缴名单
and entered her as a candidate
‪是我罔顾她的意见
for the Crown Princess selection.
‪擅自主张进行了此事
Please reprove this foolish father
‪要怪就请责怪我这没出息的父亲
for not realizing where his daughter's heart lies.
‪未能察觉女儿的心思
Please, I beg you not to do this.
‪您为何要这么做？
-Come on. -Please don't do this.
‪-快过来 ‪-请不要这样
I must hurry home. Lady So-eun awaits me!
‪我得赶紧回去了 ‪我们家小姐还在等我！
Why you…
‪你真是…
Screaming will not do you any good. Nobody can help you anymore.
‪你喊破喉咙也没人会来帮你
Your master has been demoted,
‪你家主子都返乡了
so who can possibly save you now?
‪到底谁会来帮助无依无靠的你啊？
Now, move.
‪快点走
Hurry along.
‪快跟我过来
Who may you be and what is with the imposing stance?
‪你谁啊？站在这里耍帅做什么？
Step aside.
‪让开
Must you indulge in such indecent behavior within the Capital?
‪光天化日之下在都城中心 ‪这是何等卑劣之举？叔父
You must have a lot of time on your hands.
‪您好像闲着没事做
I thought you were busy planning your wedding.
‪我以为您在忙拣择的事呢
The period of your house arrest must have been too short.
‪看来安置刑的时间太短了
If it is what you desire,
‪若叔父想要的话
I could see to it that you never leave your house again.
‪我这次可以让你永远出不了家门
I rested well thanks to you.
‪托您的福我好好休息了一番
Sitting at home all day almost gave me an itch that could kill.
‪害我浑身憋得要命
However, it will not happen again
‪不过以后不会再有这种事了
for I'm also dangling from the lifeline that's around you.
‪我现在和邸下是同一阵线的人了
Were you the one who informed the Queen Dowager about
‪将吏判的事禀告大妃殿的人
the Minister of Personnel's daughter?
‪难道就是叔父吗？
It must have broken your heart
‪您一定很伤心吧
to have found out about the involvement between your tutor
‪您的老师和差点成为世子嫔的女人
and the one you almost married.
‪竟然有一腿
Who knows? They could very well be together at this said moment.
‪他们现在说不定还在某处私通呢
And might I remind you
‪而且您似乎没搞清楚
that this girl belonged to the family who mocked yours.
‪她主子一家可是侮辱了邸下
That being said,
‪所以说
it will be in your best interest to just be about on your way.
‪请邸下继续走您的路吧
I have unfinished business with this girl, you see.
‪我跟这孩子上次还有些事情没做完
Off we go.
‪我们走
Let go of her.
‪放开你的手
Disobey my orders
‪否则
and you will be taught the weight of the law.
‪我会当场让你见识国法的威严
Are you threatening a royal relative
‪您现在是为了区区一个丫头
in the name of defending this lowlife?
‪胁迫我这个宗亲吗？
She is one of my precious people.
‪她是我宝贵的百姓
I will not stand idly by when an attempt
‪有人要在我面前伤害朝鲜百姓
to harm my people is being made.
‪我绝对不会容许
Right, of course.
‪好啦
All right.
‪好吧
Are you all right?
‪你没事吧？
Yes, Your Royal Highness.
‪是 邸下
so you may join me.
‪和我们一起走吧
That reminds me!
‪对了
I hope you're aware…
‪您知道吗？
of Lord Sangheon's promise to reward me for gaining the leverage on Minister Shin
‪为奖励我让吏判贬职的功劳 ‪尚宪君大监…
which resulted in his demotion.
‪答应要给我个官职
We should go.
‪我们走吧
I heard you saved my maid.
‪听说您救了我们家的孩子
Words cannot possibly convey my gratitude.
‪真不知该如何感谢您
I heard you will soon be returning to your hometown.
‪我听说你近日就要返乡了
Forgive me, Your Royal Highness.
‪臣女惶恐 邸下
I wronged you in the severest of ways
‪我对邸下犯了…
and should never be pardoned.
‪不可饶恕的大罪
Hardly.
‪别这么说
One's heart is not an object that can be controlled at will.
‪人心并非我们所能控制的
That day,
‪你那天
I was grateful for the honesty you displayed.
‪对我坦诚相待 我反而很感谢你
I say so…
‪因为
as a coward who hid my feelings.
‪我是没勇气那么做的人
If it were not for these circumstances,
‪假如不是在这种情况下认识
I even thought of how we could have been
‪我们也许会成为好友吧
good friends.
‪我曾经这样想过
A friendship between
‪当然
a man and a woman may not be possible, but still.
‪男女之间是不存在纯友谊的
Anyway…
‪请务必
I wish for your good health and peaceful life.
‪保重身体 祝你一切顺利
My father will be home soon.
‪我父亲就快回来了
Please let him know I send him my best regards…
‪请小姐代我向吏判大监问好
and that I await the day we meet again.
‪期待再次与他相见的那天
Jan-i?
‪潺怡
Jan-i!
‪潺怡！
Oh, no. Jan-i…
‪不可以
Jan-i…
‪潺怡
…and the one you almost married.
‪竟然有一腿
Who knows? They could very well be together at this said moment.
‪他们现在说不定还在某处私通呢
Jan-i!
‪潺怡！
EPISODE 11
‪第 11 集
Damn it.
‪该死
How dare you?
‪你干了什么好事？
What is the meaning of this?
‪您突然是怎么了？
Why am I enraged?
‪你问我怎么了？
Because a girl died.
‪有人死了
An innocent girl died!
‪一个无辜的人死了！
Why did you kill her?
‪你为何杀了她？
She didn't do anything wrong! Why?
‪她又没有做错什么！
Let me go first…
‪您先放开我
Being the Crown Prince
‪即使您贵为邸下
doesn't give you the right to disrespect your elder!
‪也不能没大没小地劈头就来教训我！
This time around,
‪我这一次
I will not let your behavior slide.
‪绝对不会姑息这件事
Damn it.
‪可恶
I already told you everything.
‪我不是说了吗？
It is true that I passed the house at that hour,
‪我当时确实路过了那里
but I did not kill anyone.
‪但我没有杀人啊
Who would be crazy enough to kill a slave in broad daylight?
‪我又不是疯了 ‪怎么会在光天化日之下杀害奴婢？
Why would I waste my time and energy on a life worth nothing?
‪我何必为了一条不值钱的命 ‪白费力气呢？
That's just preposterous.
‪简直太荒谬了
Do you not agree?
‪难道不是吗？
Then how do you explain the scratches on your face
‪那么你脸上的伤口
and this jade button that was found with the victim?
‪以及这个掉落的玉贯子要怎么解释？
Oh, this?
‪这个啊？
That stings.
‪该死
I already told you that the lowlife scratched me.
‪这也是那丫头乱抓我 ‪才会变成这样的啊
She is as feisty as her lady.
‪简直跟她主子一样泼辣
How dare that wench harm a royal relative.
‪竟敢弄伤王亲的身体
Right here.
‪看到没？
Do you see this?
‪您看到了吗？
It is not I but she who should be answering to her crime.
‪该被问罪的不是我 而是那个丫头
Death does not excuse anyone!
‪死了就没事了吗？
The girl was stabbed to death.
‪死去的孩子身上遭凶器刺伤
Have the coroner specify a murder weapon.
‪请派检尸官确认凶器
The killer's residence must be thoroughly searched.
‪并且必须仔细搜索凶手的住处
Hold on to these.
‪东西拿好
These are for the physician.
‪这些是要给医员的
You will be all right now, so do not worry.
‪你会好起来的 别担心
Get in line, people!
‪请大家排队
Our physician hates when people cut in line.
‪我们医员最讨厌有人插队了
Is this where I can find the acupuncturist from Hanyang?
‪这里是来自汉阳的针灸师开的对吧？
Yes, you are in the right place.
‪对 你找对地方了
From what I hear, the physician has almost godly powers.
‪据说医员的针灸技术十分了得
Yes, that is right. Now, get in line.
‪对啦 没错 快去排队
-But the line is too long. -Please get in line.
‪-队伍怎么排这么长啊？ ‪-请过去排队
Do not cut in line.
‪不要插队
-Goodness. -Goodness me.
‪-真是的 ‪-天啊
Just how long is this line?
‪队伍到底有多长？
Get behind me, woman.
‪排在我后面
Do you remember what I told you not to eat?
‪老爷爷 记得我叫你别吃什么吗？
What was that? A fire poker?
‪什么？火钳吗？
No, food. What are you not supposed to eat?
‪我是说食物 不能吃的食物
Food?
‪食物啊？
Yes, food. Meat and sugary food. You must not consume those.
‪就是食物 肉类和甜食都不要吃
Fish?
‪鱼？
No, meat. And also sugary food.
‪肉类还有甜食
Right, I hear you.
‪好啦
My goodness.
‪唉唷
My dear,
‪老婆
he said I should eat a lot of meat and sugary food.
‪医员叫我多吃肉类和甜食
No, that's not…
‪不对 那个…
Those are what you should not eat!
‪我是要你别吃啊！
Can you wait here a second?
‪你在这里等一下
Have this brewed in warm water
‪用温水煎这个药草
and dab the itchy skin with it.
‪并拿来清洗搔痒部位
Oh, and make sure he doesn't scratch.
‪还有啊 绝对不能让他抓痒
When the itch gets unbearable…
‪你每次很痒的时候…
Count to five like so.
‪数到五就好 知道吗？
-All right.
‪-好的 ‪-好
Thank you so much.
‪谢谢你
The pleasure is mine.
‪谢谢你喔
Can you wait over there?
‪你先到旁边等一下
-Sure. -Good.
‪-好 ‪-嗯
My lord, please. You must get in line like the rest.
‪这位书生 你要排队啊
Hyun?
‪显
Ji-un.
‪郑至韵
I sure am glad to see you.
‪你来得正好
No wonder I dreamed of a snake crawling into the yard.
‪我昨晚梦见一条蟒蛇爬进院子里
I was foreseeing the visit of a special someone.
‪原来是有贵人前来的征兆 快过来
Have a seat.
‪坐吧
Here.
‪来
You can do it, right? I'm putting my trust in you.
‪你可以吧？就交给你了
Next!
‪下一位请进
Goodness.
‪唉唷
My goodness.
‪怎么回事？
What…
‪叔叔…
What happened to your face?
‪你的脸怎么变成这样了？
Where did this happen to you?
‪在哪里弄的？过来一点
Here. Take one.
‪来 给你 吃一个吧
How did you even find this place?
‪你到底是怎么找到这个地方的？
I got lost looking for it.
‪我不晓得在巷弄里绕了几次
It sure was a hassle.
‪还以为我要死了
Gosh!
‪真是的
Will you stop with the mumbling and grumbling, Lord Jaeun?
‪拜托你别再抱怨了 君大监
You sure grumble a lot for someone who came here to lend a hand.
‪既然都来帮助下乡的朋友了 ‪话怎么还这么多？
Lend a hand? I only came by to see how you were.
‪我哪是来帮你的？我只是来打个招呼
If I had known it was this secluded,
‪早知道是如此偏僻的地方
I would have asked you to meet me elsewhere.
‪就和你约在别处见面了
Well…
‪唉唷
The flowers are a beauty.
‪这里花草很漂亮嘛
Even those with lingering diseases
‪就连缠绵病榻的人们
leave this place with their faces slightly flushed.
‪离开时也变得面色红润
It must not be so bad here.
‪看来待在这里还不错
Of course. It's nice.
‪那当然 很好啊
Clean water, fresh air, and good people.
‪水质绝佳、空气新鲜、人心和善
If I had known about this place, I would have come sooner.
‪要是知道这里这么好 我就早点来了
I am glad to see that you are doing well.
‪太好了 你看起来过得很好
The Crown Prince is well, right?
‪邸下过得很好吧？
Is everything all right?
‪没什么事吧？
Don't worry about the palace.
‪别担心宫里的事
By the way, your mother requested that I deliver this to you.
‪对了 你母亲嘱咐我把这个转交给你
My mother?
‪我娘？
What weird object did she…
‪她又拿了什么奇怪的…
What is this?
‪这是什么？
A clairvoyant bodhisattva wrote it for you.
‪她说是很灵验的菩萨写给你的
She said you would know how to use it.
‪还说你知道使用方法
Unbelievable.
‪唉唷
The so-called bodhisattva of Mount Cheongryong.
‪那该死的青龙山菩萨
She fell for his tricks again.
‪我娘又被骗了
How about you take it instead?
‪你要戴吗？显
You see, one must carry this on his undergarment.
‪这是要挂在衬裤上的
Go ahead. Let me help you attach it.
‪这给你吧 我帮你戴上
-Get that away from me. -Come on. Don't be like this, Lord Jaeun.
‪-拿开 ‪-唉唷 不要这样嘛 君大监
A man engaged in state affairs must stay healthy, don't you say?
‪替国家做事的人身体要健康啊
Why you…
‪-你这小子… ‪-君大监 快过来
Get that away from me.
‪喂 还不给我拿走？
Come on. Don't be like that.
‪可恶 给我过来
Allow me to attach it to your undergarment, Lord Jaeun.
‪我帮你挂在衬裤上 君大监
Get back here.
‪过来这里
The flowers have bloomed beautifully.
‪花开得很漂亮
I hope all went well on your trip for the Ministry of Rites.
‪礼曹之事顺利解决完毕了吗？
It did. Where I traveled was close to where Royal Tutor Jung set up his clinic,
‪是 正好郑司书落脚之处
so I dropped by to see him.
‪就在那附近 我还见了他一面
I see.
‪原来如此
He seemed well.
‪他似乎过得很好
Staying healthy and keeping busy.
‪身体健康 生活忙碌
I am relieved to hear that.
‪那真是万幸
How has it been for you, Your Royal Highness?
‪邸下 你还好吗？
What do you mean?
‪你是指什么？
I know that you two grew quite close.
‪两位之前相处得蛮好的
I thought you might be feeling lonely.
‪我想你心里可能会感到空虚
Not at all.
‪怎么会呢？
NOKUNGAK
‪（绿云阁）
Wind chimes?
‪风铃？
The sounds they make
‪听到那个声音
take me back to a moment in life I miss.
‪就仿佛回到某个怀念的时刻
A time when I had no worries
‪那是什么都不用担心
and could spend all day doing nothing.
‪什么都不用做
That moment in my childhood
‪非常年幼时的
is where I am taken to.
‪某个时刻
Don't they sound similar to this?
‪不觉得跟这声音也很像吗？
The sounds made by the wind chimes which you enjoy.
‪听起来就像邸下喜欢的风铃声
That being said, how about we clink our glasses once more.
‪来 大家再来干一杯吧
Cheers!
‪干杯
The section chief of the Ministry of War was found dead at the ministry office.
‪兵曹正郎是在兵曹的官厅内 ‪遭逢变故的
How has there not been a commotion
‪官厅内发生凶杀案
when a murder occurred in a government office?
‪怎么没有引起骚动？
I presume it was per Commander Yoon's orders.
‪我猜是内禁卫长所下的令
In other words, it is His Majesty who wishes to keep it quiet.
‪主上并不希望把案件闹大
And regarding that, one hopes to share information.
‪关于这一点 我有件事要向您禀报
Un-am who took his own life recently,
‪不久前自缢的沄岩
the deceased Governor Kwon of Hamgyong Province,
‪已故的咸镜道观察使权世谦
and now the section chief.
‪以及这次的兵曹正郎
They all gave the decisive statements
‪全都是在十年前翊善推鞠时
during Preceptor Kang's interrogation ten years ago.
‪做出关键证词之人
Are you saying that someone has been murdering them
‪你言下之意是 ‪有人因为十年前翊善的事
to avenge the preceptor who died ten years ago?
‪正在四处杀人吗？
It will be in your best interest to take precautions, my lord.
‪我想大监最好也小心为妙
Look here. Step aside!
‪注意 让一让
Make way.
‪让出路来
What was that?
‪发生了什么事？
An assassin, my lord.
‪有刺客
Take Lord Sangheon to safety!
‪快护送大监到安全的地方！
Explain yourself!
‪怎么回事？
What brings you here?
‪你怎么会在这里？
A suspicious man attacked the Left State Councilor.
‪有可疑人士盯上左相大监
I will explain in due time.
‪之后再跟你解释
Someone suspicious?
‪可疑人士？
But no one is around.
‪这里没有半个人啊
I am also curious as to
‪我才想问内禁卫长
what you are doing here at this time of day, Commander Yoon.
‪这个时间为何恰好在这里？
I was patrolling outside the palace walls.
‪我正在巡视宫外
It surely is odd
‪真是奇怪了
for you to be on patrol on this side of the gate.
‪内禁卫长竟会亲自来此巡视
Anyone suspicious will be mine to apprehend,
‪若有可疑之人 我会将其逮捕
so be on your way.
‪你请回吧
Kim Ga-on was able to get away.
‪金佳稳已顺利脱身了
I see.
‪好
You did well.
‪辛苦了
One must ask.
‪不过
Do you still intend to keep him in the palace?
‪您打算继续将他留在宫里吗？
It may endanger you as well.
‪这样您或许也会有危险
Until I say otherwise,
‪在我再次下令前
keep a close eye on him.
‪多多注意那孩子
I will not allow…
‪我不允许…
another soul to be hurt.
‪再有任何人受伤了
You are staring, Uncle.
‪怎么一直盯着我瞧？
A nephew visiting his uncle is not all that surprising.
‪侄儿只是来叔父家打声招呼罢了
You are not one to have come by without a reason.
‪你应该不会无缘无故地来找我
Let me see.
‪我看看
His Royal Highness must have put you up to this.
‪是世子派你来的吧？
You were ordered to find out about what happened to the girl named Jan-i.
‪要你来打听关于潺怡那丫头的事
I see you are not as dense as you used to be.
‪叔父察言观色的能力比以往好多了
That being said,
‪所以说
why did you kill the girl?
‪你到底为何要杀了她？
Since Lord Sangheon is now looking out for you,
‪反正你背后有尚宪君大监当靠山
there will be no harm in telling me.
‪你应该可以告诉我吧
Do you really wish to know
‪你真的想知道…
why I did it?
‪我为何会那么做吗？
Because I was angry.
‪我那么做是因为太气愤了
Anger swept over me.
‪我很气愤
I could not take
‪看见世子那么自以为是
seeing the Crown Prince acting all righteously.
‪我实在气到忍无可忍
Still…
‪不过
killing her was never my intention.
‪我原本不打算杀了她
If anything, she is to blame for harming a royal relative.
‪都怪她碰到我贵为王亲的身体
Gosh, that's bitter.
‪唉唷 好苦啊
Absolutely bitter.
‪好苦
Bring me better food, damn it!
‪喂！重新上一份菜肴！
Anyway, eat up. Enjoy.
‪你吃啊 快吃吧
Damn it.
‪可恶
What?
‪嗯？
What a relief.
‪吓死我了
Thank you…
‪多亏你
for leading me to where it lies, Uncle.
‪我找到东西了 叔父
That hurts.
‪好痛
Don't just stand there. Protect me.
‪愣着做什么？快保护我
It is the Crown Prince. Sheathe your swords.
‪是世子邸下 把刀放下
Damn it!
‪该死！
Now that I have evidence,
‪既然我找到了物证
I doubt my grandfather can continue to offer his protection.
‪我外祖父应该就无法再袒护你了
I damaged the property of the Minister of Personnel
‪我损耗了吏判家的财产
and will accept the punishment for my actions.
‪那么付出相应的代价不就行了吗？
Anyone guilty of murder will be sentenced to execution by beheading.
‪凡夺去他人生命者 皆将处斩首之刑
The deceased girl was also one of the people.
‪死去的那孩子也是朝鲜的百姓
Thus, your actions should be dealt with accordingly.
‪因此理当依杀人罪来惩治你
Murder?
‪怎么能说是杀人罪呢？
Surely you must not mean
‪您该不会为了一个小奴婢
that I, your uncle, should pay for her life with mine.
‪要拿我这个叔父的命来抵偿吧？
It is common knowledge that certain lives weigh more than others!
‪再怎么说世间万物还是有轻重之分！
Are you saying…
‪所以
that your life matters more
‪你的命比较宝贵
than the deceased girl's?
‪死去奴婢的命就比较卑贱吗？
Well, isn't that common knowledge?
‪那…那不是理所当然的吗？
I am of royal blood
‪我是王室宗亲
and the uncle to His Royal Highness.
‪更何况还是邸下的叔父
If that is true, then being the Crown Prince,
‪那么与叔父的命比起来
my life would be worth much more than yours.
‪我这个世子的性命应该重要多了
However, you carried out acts that could harm me.
‪但你竟敢加害于我？
I don't quite follow.
‪那是什么意思？
Once at the royal hunting site
‪在讲武场一次
and once during my bath.
‪在汤浴场又一次
The girl had the audacity to harm a man of royal blood.
‪那丫头斗胆伤害了王室宗亲的身体
She was as good as dead anyway!
‪她终究难逃一死
If that can be said about her,
‪那照这么说来
you could also be killed right here as well.
‪叔父在这丧命也没什么不可以吧？
No, wait.
‪等等
Please do not tell me
‪你该不会
you are not realizing the severity of this matter
‪还天真地以为
and are naive enough to believe I would not kill my uncle.
‪侄儿不会杀了叔父吧？
No, wait.
‪慢着
Why are you doing this?
‪您为何要这么做呢？
Your Royal Highness.
‪邸下
Please have mercy on me,
‪请饶命 邸下
I was wrong.
‪我错了
If you wish to beg for your life,
‪你若想求我饶命
do it in her presence, not mine.
‪对象不该是我 ‪而是死去的那孩子才对
Visit her grave
‪到那孩子的坟前
and bow for her forgiveness.
‪向她行礼赎罪
Do so, and I will at least spare you your life…
‪那我不会即刻在这里要了你的命
and turn you over to the State Tribunal.
‪而是会乖乖将你交给义禁府
Wait. Hold on.
‪等等 您这是
Did you just order me to bow to a slave's grave?
‪要我向奴婢的坟墓行礼吗？
Why?
‪怎么？
Is it something you cannot do?
‪你办不到吗？
Of course not. I will heed your command.
‪不 我去 我去就是了
I will do it.
‪我会去的
You had him kneel!
‪下跪？
You had a royal relative kneel in front of a slave's grave.
‪你居然让王室宗亲 ‪在区区一个奴婢坟前下跪？
How am I supposed to understand this rash behavior?
‪行事怎么如此鲁莽呢？
Uncle abused his power as a royal relative
‪叔父利用身为王亲的权力
and took an innocent life.
‪夺去一条无辜的生命
I believed he should at least
‪因此孩儿认为
atone and apologize for his actions.
‪他至少要为此赔罪才是
He has been this way for years now.
‪昌沄君的恶劣品行已持续许久
You should have held back.
‪你得忍下来啊
As the Crown Prince, it is your duty to uphold the code of morals.
‪世子应该带头恪守纲常之道
What brought on this lack of judgment?
‪怎会犯下此等失误呢？
It was not a misjudgment.
‪那并非失误
All I did was act dutifully.
‪孩儿只是做了该做的事罢了
I heeded Father's guidance to serve our people
‪孩儿遵从了父王 ‪要我为百姓服务的旨意
and Grandmother's guidance regarding my duty
‪也遵照王祖母的意思
to uphold the dignity of our royal blood.
‪维护了王室权威
It is why
‪因此
I do not feel even the slightest bit ashamed.
‪孩儿对自己的行为并不感到惭愧
-Crown Prince! -This matter
‪-世子 ‪-这件事
will be mine to sort out.
‪我会处理好
You are dismissed.
‪你先出去吧
Was this an act to become a benevolent king?
‪您想成为圣君吗？
You should have also kept in mind
‪您怎么没想到
that your actions could provoke other royal relatives
‪您的举动可能会惹怒
and members of the nobility.
‪宗亲和士大夫呢？
This nation only maintains its peace
‪这个国家之所以能够维持运转
because the law binding different social classes
‪正是因为身份贵贱的秩序
is never disrupted.
‪有条不紊
One who is next in line for the throne
‪将来要成为君王的人
should not disrupt that order over the petty life of a slave.
‪不该为了一条 ‪微不足道的生命而破坏秩序
A petty life, did you say?
‪您说那是微不足道的生命吗？
What I mean is that you were wrong
‪臣言下之意是
to have gotten involved in the murder of a lowly girl.
‪您不该干涉一介卑贱丫头的生死
There is no such thing as a petty life.
‪世上没有所谓微不足道的生命
And there is not a single person who should die for no reason.
‪也没有无缘无故就得死去的生命
No one…
‪任何人
has the right to disregard another's life.
‪都不得任意践踏别人的性命
No one.
‪无论是谁都不行
-The Crown Prince did what? -You heard me.
‪-世子邸下吗？ ‪-是啊
Word has been traveling all across the Capital.
‪现在那件事在全都城引起了骚动
The Crown Prince who made a mockery out of his uncle.
‪说世子羞辱了自己的叔父
Some are slandering him for violating moral principles.
‪也有人责骂世子犯了纲常罪
But only nobles, if you ask me.
‪但那都是两班们的意见
People like us could not be more satisfied.
‪我们这种人全都觉得大快人心
Never have I ever been this fond of a ruler before.
‪唉唷 从来没见过那么好的君王
So what happened?
‪那后来怎么样了？
Insulting a royal relative
‪毕竟是对王室宗亲动了手
must have put His Royal Highness in trouble.
‪邸下应该会遇上很多麻烦
You never seem intrigued when it comes to the Capital,
‪你平常一副不关心都城事情的样子
but you prick up your ears when the Crown Prince is mentioned.
‪但一提到世子邸下 ‪你就开始感兴趣了
Well…
‪不是那样的
I hope you are well,
‪您没事吧？
Your Royal Highness.
‪邸下
Why are you outside and not in bed sleeping?
‪你怎么又不睡 跑来外面呢？
Even when I am here,
‪即使来到这里
all I do is think about you.
‪我还是一心只想着邸下
I am worried…
‪我既担心您
and I miss you.
‪也很思念您
Says the man who chose to move out here.
‪所以你才会来这里吗？
A place this secluded.
‪到这如此偏僻的地方
I wish to be by your side,
‪我想陪在您身边
take you in my arms,
‪想将您抱在怀里
have conversations,
‪想这样和您相视谈天
and be together with you.
‪想和您待在一起
Goodness.
‪等等 那个人…
Hello?
‪喂
LAST WILL AND TESTAMENT
‪（遗书）
You came, Great Lord Changcheon.
‪你来了 大监
You must have a good reason for summoning me up here.
‪找我来这种地方做什么？
As if there must be one.
‪没有别的意思
One only hoped you would join me on a hunt.
‪我只是想邀你一同打猎
Hunting does not intrigue me at all.
‪我对打猎不感兴趣
Especially a hunting trip accompanied by royal relatives.
‪尤其不想和宗亲们一起打猎
Yes, of course.
‪我想也是
Prince Jehyeon is the apple of His Majesty's eye,
‪殿下对齐贤大君疼爱有加
so there is no reason for you to go out hunting.
‪所以你没必要到处寻找猎物
What are you trying to say?
‪你想说什么？
Even game that's been caught in a trap
‪即使眼前摆了一桌饭菜
is not easy to retrieve for the cowardly predator.
‪对胆小的狼而言 ‪那只是可望不可即的佳肴
What?
‪什么？
LAST WILL AND TESTAMENT
‪（遗书）
These are the last words of Lord Changun.
‪这是昌沄君大监留下的遗书
Last words?
‪遗…
The humiliation induced by the Crown Prince was unbearable for him.
‪他忍受不了邸下的羞辱 ‪因而选择自我了断
How could this have happened?
‪怎么会发生这种事？
I doubt I am the only one who is devastated by his death.
‪我不认为只有我 ‪会为叔父之死感到伤心
Moral principles were violated.
‪这可是破坏纲常之道的事情
A man of nobility knelt before a slave.
‪两班向奴婢下跪
He was humiliated by his own nephew which led him to take his own life.
‪叔父遭到侄子嘲弄 ‪最后选择自我了断
Members of the nobility cannot let this matter slide.
‪朝鲜的士大夫们可不能坐视不管
That reminds me.
‪对了
I hear that your nephew
‪听说你的侄子
is the ritual manager at the Royal Confucian Academy.
‪担任成均馆的掌议
Confucian scholars are the ones who have always corrected grave matters.
‪国家发生大事时 ‪儒生们总会带头群起进谏
Please make sure this reaches your nephew.
‪将叔父留下的那封书信 ‪转交给你侄子吧
It will serve us greatly.
‪我相信会很有帮助的
Lord Changun, whom the Crown Prince commanded to disrupt Confucianism order,
‪“奉世子邸下之命 ‪破坏儒教秩序的昌沄君
lamented over his humiliation by taking his own life.
‪因受尽屈辱而自我了断
The Crown Prince is one who should lead an exemplary life.
‪世子未尽到做为百姓榜样的本分
However, the entire nation is confused and is feeling unsettled
‪因破坏儒教秩序 惊动全国上下
over his decision to disrupt the Confucian order.
‪致使人心躁动不安
The sinister way of humiliation
‪再加上世子侮辱叔父
which led his uncle to death has reached the heavens
‪致其身亡 悖伦罪行重大
and we are gravely worried that its wrath will fall on the people.
‪臣等忧心朝鲜的所有百姓 ‪需承担一切罪行
If His Majesty wishes to set order to the nation
‪若殿下也愿意树立国家秩序
and if he honors the Confucian law,
‪尊敬儒教的制度
the wisest decision will be
‪那么收回世子的职牒
to strip the Crown Prince of his title and depose him.
‪并下令废黜世子才是明智之举
Please punish the Crown Prince
‪恳请殿下严惩
for shaking the foundation of the Confucian order.
‪动摇儒教根基的世子邸下”
-Please punish the Crown Prince.
‪-恳请殿下严惩
Who was it?
‪是谁？
Pardon?
‪什么？
Who was it that rallied the Confucian scholars?
‪是谁召集儒生行动的？
Well…
‪那个…
I am also flustered by what is happening and--
‪微臣现在也感到十分惊慌…
Did you believe this would promote Prince Jehyeon to Crown Prince?
‪你认为这么做 ‪齐贤大君就能坐上世子之位吗？
I am lost for words at your accusation, Your Majesty.
‪您怎么这么说呢？殿下
Please believe me when I say I did not know.
‪微臣着实不清楚此事
It is common knowledge
‪所有人都知道
that your nephew is the ritual manager at the Royal Confucian Academy.
‪府院君的侄子是成均馆掌议
How long do you intend to deceive me?
‪你真的打算继续蒙骗我吗？
My nephew may be the ritual manager
‪微臣的侄子确实是掌议
but who am I to stop the Confucian scholars
‪但儒生们不满世子违背常理
from leaving their posts to raise their concerns
‪并且决定卷堂的举动
regarding the disobedient act against our class system?
‪微臣怎么阻止得了呢？殿下
What is the meaning of this?
‪这是在做什么？
You will see to it that the scholars leave the gate.
‪请府院君负责让儒生全数撤退
Right now!
‪立刻就去！
How dare you…
‪你竟敢…
Deploy the soldiers, Your Majesty.
‪请殿下部署士兵
Those who are dishonoring the Crown Prince on palace grounds
‪必须将掌控宫廷 ‪与侮辱世子邸下的那些人
must be found guilty of treason!
‪依谋反罪加以严惩！
Whether it is treason or not is my decision to make.
‪是否为谋反由我来判断
I will see to this matter personally, so I advise you to step away!
‪此事我会决定 尚宪君 你退下吧
Apprehend those who led this strike and hang their heads on a pike.
‪请殿下捉拿主谋 将其人头取下
If necessary, I will deploy the soldiers myself.
‪倘若有需要 臣会动员士兵
Anyone who speaks of deposing the Crown Prince
‪将煽动废黜世子的人全数捉拿起来
shall have their mouths ripped open and tongues cut off.
‪撕烂他们的嘴 拔掉他们的舌头
Explain this to me.
‪这是什么东西？
Why do you have the appeal regarding the dethronement of the Crown Prince?
‪儒生要废黜世子邸下的上疏 ‪为何在王兄房里？
It speaks for itself.
‪这样不是很明显吗？
His Royal Highness acted hastily.
‪这次是邸下过于轻率了
It was a grave misjudgment on his part.
‪他犯了很严重的错误
Is this why you met with Great Lord Changcheon?
‪那你也是因为这件事 ‪才会见畅天君大监吗？
How could you do something like this?
‪你怎么能这么做？
Why are you orchestrating such defiance?
‪为何你要带头做这种事？
Until when will you only take the Crown Prince's side?
‪我才想问你究竟要偏袒世子到何时？
It is time you face the facts.
‪拜托你认清现实
Your uncle is dead.
‪你的叔父死了
And it is over for the Crown Prince.
‪世子将不再握有权势了
Brother.
‪王兄
It was all supposed to be mine.
‪那原本是我的位置
The palace was home to our father who was the Crown Prince,
‪这座宫原本是身为世子的父亲
to me his eldest son,
‪和曾是元孙的我
you, and our mother.
‪还有年幼的你及我们母亲 ‪一家生活的地方
Do not be this way.
‪请别这么做
Please stop this. Please.
‪拜托你停手 我求你了
Unfortunately, I cannot.
‪很可惜我办不到
There is nothing I can do to stop the scholars now.
‪我现在也无法阻止儒生们了
Please dethrone the Crown Prince and strip him of his title.
‪请收回世子的职牒 并下令废黜世子
-Please dethrone him!
‪-请废黜世子！
Punish the Crown Prince for shaking the foundation of the Confucian order.
‪恳请殿下严惩 ‪动摇儒教根基的世子邸下
How can they be this cruel?
‪读书人怎能说出那么狠毒的话呢？
Have the Crown Prince
‪恳请殿下向侮辱叔父
take responsibility for the death of his own uncle.
‪导致其丧命 ‪犯下悖伦罪行的世子邸下问罪
-He must take responsibility.
‪-恳请殿下问罪！
What if you swallowed your pride
‪您要不要眼睛一闭
and asked His Majesty for forgiveness?
‪去大殿认错呢？
You don't know what the outcome of this ordeal could be.
‪再这样下去真不晓得会发生什么事情
Do you two also think I went too far?
‪你们也认为我太过分了吗？
That's not it.
‪不是那样的
You were able to hold yourself back until now.
‪您一直以来不是都好好忍住了吗？
But how come you couldn't this time?
‪但这次为何做不到？
I was going to.
‪我原本也打算忍下来
I guess I could have.
‪我应该能忍住的
But this time around, I did not want to.
‪但我这次不想那么做
She had her life taken from her because she was of low birth…
‪那个因为身份卑微而不得不死的孩子
and I had to die because I was born a girl.
‪和因为是女儿身就得死的我
What makes us any different?
‪有什么不同呢？
Your Royal Highness…
‪邸下
If I had turned a blind eye yet again,
‪若我这次又假装若无其事
then for another ten years…
‪那么往后十年…
No…
‪不
Until the end of my days, my life would have been filled
‪或许是永远
to stay alive.
‪就没了任何意义不是吗？
What kind of a life would that be?
‪那种人生有什么意义呢？
That thought crossed my mind.
‪我突然有了这种想法
Pretending not to see and hear things
‪仅仅为了守住这个位置
for the sake of keeping my place in the palace?
‪而选择闭上眼睛、捂住耳朵过日子
What meaning is there in that?
‪究竟有什么意义呢？
The scholars' reactions…
‪看着现在那些儒生
prove to me
‪此处似乎
that the code our people live by
‪仍和我出生当时
has not changed since I was born.
‪没有任何改变
You did well, Your Royal Highness.
‪您做得很好
The Crown Princess Consort
‪嫔宫娘娘
would not have wanted your life to be like that.
‪肯定也不希望邸下的人生变成那样
If she had been alive,
‪若娘娘还在世 她一定也会说
she would have said
‪您是对的
that you were right
‪您做得很好
and that you acted properly.
‪她会这样鼓励您的
So please do not be hard on yourself.
‪所以请您不要自责
Eunuch Hong and I
‪我和洪内官直到最后
will always stand by you, Your Royal Highness.
‪都会遵从邸下的旨意
JASEONDANG
‪（资善堂）
Hyun?
‪王兄
I see you have yet to turn in for the night.
‪你还没睡吗？
How can one sleep with all the commotion outside?
‪外头如此喧闹 ‪我怎么可能轻易入睡呢？
I feel ashamed.
‪真是丢人
You always seem to catch me in these embarrassing moments.
‪怎么老是让王兄见到我这副模样呢？
There is something I must confess to you.
‪我有一件事要向你坦承
I met you for the first time when I was 14.
‪我在14岁那年第一次见到邸下
Your two eyes were deep and as clear as the clearest of seas.
‪你的双眼虽十分深邃 ‪清澈得深不见底
However, what filled them…
‪但眼神中却充满了
was an unexpected level of caution.
‪莫名的警戒心
How could I not recognize your eyes
‪我和世孙大人犹如亲兄弟
when you are like a brother to me?
‪怎么可能认不出他的眼神呢？
Your face, your voice,
‪虽然你们的长相、声音
and even your gait were the same,
‪甚至连走路的姿势都一模一样
but…
‪但是
you weren't the young prince I grew up with.
‪邸下分明不是我所认识的世孙
All this time,
‪你早就…
you knew everything?
‪知道一切了吗？
I was confused at first
‪我起初感到很混乱
and then fear overwhelmed me.
‪后来则是感到恐惧
And when I met you once again,
‪而后再次见到邸下时
I wanted to protect you.
‪我就想守护你了
The child who practiced archery all night despite the blisters on her hands.
‪彻夜练箭练到手皮开肉绽的那个孩子
The child who rose to her feet
‪即使跌倒骨折
even when the fall broke her bone.
‪依然咬牙起身的那个孩子
The child who was left alone
‪在他人无法想象的艰难环境中
I made a promise to myself that I would protect that child.
‪我下定决心要守护她
Hyun…
‪王兄
If you are dethroned,
‪一旦遭到废黜
the only thing that awaits you would be death.
‪等着你的就只有死路一条
Even if you are lucky enough not to be deposed,
‪不 即使你运气好 没遭到废黜
how do you expect to manage the many hardships that lie in your way?
‪那你要如何面对 ‪日后等着你的那些事呢？
You may have been able to fool others into believing you are a man until now,
‪虽然你以女儿身尽力苦撑到现在
but it will not be as easy moving forward.
‪但未来只会更加困难
I am sure you are aware
‪秘密一旦曝光
of how this revelation could cost you your life.
‪相信你也很清楚你可能性命不保
What is it…
‪你到底…
that you actually want to say to me?
‪想跟我说什么？
Do you remember how I said that the sea awaits at the far end of the path
‪还记得我说过 ‪你无法再向前走的那条路尽头
you weren't able to once take?
‪有一片大海吗？
Currently docked there is a boat with big sails.
‪那里有一艘大帆船
You should leave on it.
‪搭上那艘船离开吧
Wherever you wish to go,
‪无论你想去何处
I will be by your side.
‪我都会奉陪到底
Subtitle translation by: Hye-lim Park
‪字幕翻译：钟见悦